<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the generall assises in Warwicke, the third of March, being the first Friday in Lent. 1619. By Samuel Burton, Archdeacon of Gloucester. Seene and allowed by authoritie</title>
            <author>Burton, Samuel, 1568 or 9-1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107146</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842848</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842848</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7541</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17315)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7541)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1371:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the generall assises in Warwicke, the third of March, being the first Friday in Lent. 1619. By Samuel Burton, Archdeacon of Gloucester. Seene and allowed by authoritie</title>
                  <author>Burton, Samuel, 1568 or 9-1634.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby for Nathaniel Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preached in 1620, Lady Day dating.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7541:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE GENERALL ASSISES IN WARWICKE, the third of March, being the <hi>firſt Friday in Lent.</hi> 1619.</p>
            <p>By SAMVEL BVRTON, Archdeacon <hi>of Glouceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seene and allowed by Authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Stansby</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter.</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:7541:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7541:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For he is the Miniſter of God to thee for thy good. But if thou doe euill, feare: for he beareth not the ſword in vaine. For he is the Miniſter of God to take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on him that doth euill.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE light of the Goſpell did no ſooner begin to breake forth of Iury and to ſhine vnto the Gentiles, but preſently this ſcandall was rayſed againſt the Profeſſors of it, that they were <hi>Nouatores rerum,</hi> Innouators of States, and Trumpeters of ſedition. Of which ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall I cannot ſay, that it was merely <hi>ſcandalum accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> a ſcandall taken by the Heathen. For indeed it was in ſome ſort, <hi>ſcandalum datum,</hi> a ſcandall giuen: Not by the true Profeſſors of the name of Chriſt, but by the Iewes firſt. Who, becauſe they were the ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> did therefore imagine themſelues to bee the true owners of the whole earth, and the only men that ought to rule in it. And ſecondly, by ſome falſe Apoſtles, blind and fooliſh Teachers, who, (becauſe Chriſt in his life time had ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Si filius vos liberauerit, verè liberi eritis;</hi> if the Sonne doe make you free, then are you free indeed: And becauſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7541:3"/>he ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi> (as it is recorded in the 17. of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew; Ergo liberi ſunt filij,</hi> then are the children free) did out of theſe two places deliuer this for currant Doctrine, That Chriſtians are and ought to bee free from ſubiection, free from tribute. Suppoſing that Chriſt in the former place had ſpoken of ciuill and corporall freedome; and in the later, of all ſorts of Chriſtians: whereas it is plaine and euident, that in the former he ſpeaketh only of freedome from ſinne, and from the curſe of the Law; and in the later, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of himſelfe; as he was the Sonne of God and King of Iſrael. This Doctrine therefore being altogether falſe and wicked, and the ſcandall that grew from it, like to proue pernicious to the Church: was the cauſe (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> tels vs) that moued the bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to enter into this large and religious diſcourſe concerning Magiſtrates, that both the children of the Church might know their dutie, and that the enemies of it might vnderſtand, that Chriſt came not into the world to take away temporall Kingdomes, (as <hi>Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> ſpeaks) but to giue eternall; that the Doctrine of Chriſt teacheth all due obedience and ſubiection to Authoritie, and that if any had taught otherwiſe, they had not therein deliuered the true Doctrine of the Church, but their owne falſe and fooliſh fancies.</p>
            <p>Out of this diſcourſe I haue choſen this Verſe (which I haue read vnto you) for my Text at this time, as contayning fitteſt matter for this preſence. For it contayneth two generall heads: whereof the</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt is, the dignitie and high calling of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And the ſecond is, his dutie.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:7541:3"/>
            <p> His dignitie appeares in this, in that he is ſaid to be the Miniſter of God himſelfe. Which word is twice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in this Verſe. For he is ſaid to be the Miniſter of God for good: and hee is ſaid to be the Miniſter of God for vengeance. Out of which partition of his Miniſterie, ariſe two ſeuerall branches of his dutie. The firſt is, the reward of well-doing: and the ſecond is, the puniſhment of ſinne. The firſt is, the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the iuſt and innocent: and the ſecond is, the co ertion of the lewd and wicked.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Concerning the firſt, the Apoſtle tels vs, that he is the Miniſter and Seruant of God. And ſo, no doubt, is euery faithfull Chriſtian in his ſeuerall calling. But ſpecially and by prerogatiue is he that Miniſter of God, unto whom is committed either the diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Word in the Church, or the vſe and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Sword among the people. Now, if the ſeruice of God in the loweſt degree be an honourable ſeruice, and more to be deſired then the command of all the earth: then ſurely, the ſeruice of God in the higheſt degree, and chiefeſt places, (which God hath ordayned here on earth) muſt needs be the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable ſeruice, and require the greateſt reſpect and regard amongſt vs. And ſuch is the ſtate of Rulers and Gouernours; they are the Miniſters of God; they are his Deputies and Surrogats in the higheſt place, which is the ſeate of Iuſtice. And therefore, if that of the Prophet in the Pſalme, may be rightly applyed to any ſort of men, then moſt fitly to Princes and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates. That God hath made them a little lower then the Angels, and crowned them with glorie, and worſhip. For hee hath ſet them in his owne Chaire
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7541:4"/>and Iudgement ſeate; he hath placed them in his own ſtead; hee hath armed them with his owne power; he hath couered them with his owne Garment and Robe of Eſtate; hee hath girded them with his owne Sword; and hee hath honoured them with his owne Name, <hi>Ego dixi, vos Dij eſtis;</hi> I haue ſaid, yee are Gods; and yee are all the children of the moſt High.</p>
            <p>And if the dignity of this Miniſtery doe not yet ſufficiently appeare vnto vs from the Author: looke further into the effects and fruits of it <hi>Omnium domos, illius vigilia defendit; Omnium otium, illius labor; Omnium delitias, illius induſtria; Omnium vacationem, illius occupatio.</hi> It is the Magiſtrate only, that makes euery mans houſe his Caſtle; his labour makes vs all to liue at eaſe; his buſineſſe makes vs vacant; his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble procures our peace; his induſtrie maintaynes our delight; his paines brings in our profit. That wee ſit ſafely in our houſes, that wee ſleepe quietly in our beds, that we drinke the water of our owne Ciſterns, that wee eate the labour of our owne hands, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, that we dwell without feare, like <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the daies of <hi>Salomon,</hi> euery man vnder his owne Vine, and his owne Fig-tree; to whom are wee bound, and beholden vnder God for all this, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to theſe Miniſters of his (as the Apoſtle tearmes them in this place) by whoſe eyes he watcheth ouer vs, by whoſe cares he heareth our complaints, out of whoſe mouthes he giueth iudgement, by whoſe hands hee ſmiteth the wicked, and vnder the ſhadow of whoſe wings hee couereth the heads of the iuſt and innocent?</p>
            <p>But why doe I enlarge and amplifie this point?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7541:4"/>That the hearts of Magiſtrates may bee exalted, and lifted vp? Surely no: It will rather humble them if it bee well conſidered of, and make them feare and tremble at their calling. For as <hi>Hierome</hi> could ſay of the great and eminent places of the Church: <hi>Non est facile ſtare loco Pauli, tenere gradum Petri:</hi> It is not ſo eaſy a matter, as a man would thinke, to ſit in <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Chaire, or <hi>Paules;</hi> (though <hi>Simon Magus</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may thinke it a matter of eaſe only, and profit;) ſo we may ſay of theſe great and eminent places in the Common-wealth, <hi>Non est facile ſtare loco Dauidis,</hi> It is not an eaſy matter to ſit in one of <hi>Dauids</hi> thrones: the bramble perhaps may thinke it a thing of nothing, but the Fig-tree, the Oliue, and the Vine, will bee afraid to venter on it. And why? Becauſe they know what a burden and a charge belongs vnto it, and what accounts depend vpon it. For vnto whomſoeuer much is giuen, of him ſhall much bee required (ſaith our Sauiour.) God when he hath once aduanced men to places of honour and authority, when hee hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them out of the duſt and ſet them among Princes to inherit the ſeate of Glory (as <hi>Hanna</hi> ſpeaketh:) when hee hath made them Pillars of the earth, and ſet the world vpon them: he lookes that they ſhould ſerue him more ſtrictly then common and ordinary men; he lookes for more exact obedience from them, then any other. There is no kind of benefit in the world, but brings a kind of bondage with it. And much more this, the greateſt of all earthly bleſſings. And therefore of all men the Magiſtrate may beſt ſay, <hi>Beneficium accepi, libertatem amiſi:</hi> God hath aduanced me to this height, hee hath made me a Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7541:5"/>and a commander ouer others, and therefor I haue loſt a great deale of that liberty, that is left to others. <hi>Caeſari cui omnia licent, propter hoc ipſum multa non licent.</hi> Euen <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelfe, becauſe hee is aboue law becauſe he may doe all things, for this very cauſe may not doe many things, (ſaith the wiſe <hi>Seneca</hi>) many things that other men may lawfully doe. And as the reſpect of their high aduancement doth abridge their liberty, ſo doth it agrauate their ſinne. For what was it elſe that made the ſinne of <hi>Saul</hi> ſo haynous and vnpardonable in ſparing <hi>Agag</hi> and the beſt things, but only this circumſtance of his aduancement? For when thou waſt little in thine owne eyes (ſaith <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi>) thou waſt made the head of all the tribes of Iſrael. And ſo <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>Dauid.</hi> God hath annointed thee King ouer Iſrael and deliuered thee out of the hands of <hi>Saul</hi> and thou haſt ſlaine <hi>Vriah</hi> the <hi>Hittite</hi> with the ſword, euen thou, which waſt ſo much bound vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for his loue vnto thee, thou which waſt taken from the Sheep-fold and from following the Ewes to be made King ouer Iſrael, thou haſt done this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſle. Heare therefore, O yee Kings, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand; learne yee that bee Iudges of the earth. Your places are high and honourable, your power is giuen you of the Lord. But if you that bee the Miniſters of his Kingdome ſhall not iudge aright, nor keepe the Law, nor walke after the counſaile of God horribly, and fearefully ſhall he come vpon you. For a ſharpe iudgement ſhall bee to them, that are in high places, mercy will ſoone pardon the meaneſt, but mighty men ſhall be mightily tormented, (ſaith the Author of the booke of <hi>Wiſedome.</hi>)</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:7541:5"/>
            <p> Let no man therefore bee ſo idle to thinke, that where the dignitie &amp; high calling of the Magiſtrate is treated of, there is or can be any intent, or meaning in the ſpeaker, to puffe vp his heart with the breath of vanity, or that any wiſe Magiſtrate will ſuffer his heart to riſe with it. There is another end and purpoſe in it; which is our inſtruction, that we ſeing the height and excellency of his calling, and being aſſured that it is of God, might learne thereby, what honour, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſeruice, we owe vnto him. This is a point of duty, which the dignity and high calling of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate doth plainely teach vs; and as the times now are, it is a point of duty, then which there is nothing more needefull to be taught and learned.</p>
            <p>That I may ſpeake therefore briefly and diſtinctly of it: As God requires at our hands, not onely out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward obedience in our deeds and actions, but alſo that wee honour him with our words, and that our hearts be vpright in his ſight: ſo the Magiſtrate (that ſits in Gods Seate, and hath his authority in his hands) may iuſtly challenge all theſe things from vs. The very height and excellency of his calling doth enforce them all. For he is the Miniſter of God, (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) therefore wee ought to obey him. Hee is the Miniſter of God, therefore wee ought not to reproch him, or reuile him; but to ſpeake all good of him. He is the Miniſter of God, therefore we ought not to hate him, or deſpiſe him; but to carry a reuerent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and eſtimation of him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Now for the firſt of theſe; You muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that when wee ſpeake of obedience to humane Lawes, we doe not meane obedience without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7541:6"/>but obedience vnder condition and limitation. So long as the Magiſtrate commands nothing by his Lawes, that is preiudiciall to our duety towards God, ſo long we muſt obey. But if he command vs to doe thoſe things that are vnlawfull; in that caſe, in ſtead of obedience we bring ſubiection. We muſt not be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient then, but euen then we muſt bee ſubiect. In all other caſes; in matters that are apparently good, in ciuill offices, in affaires of the Common-wealth, in matters of iuſtice, and in all ſuch things as are in their owne nature indifferent (and thoſe are ſuch, as are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded nor forbidden in the Word of God) we muſt not only be ſubiect, but obedient alſo. Giue vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars</hi> (ſaith <hi>Christ.</hi>) Submit your ſelues to all manner of ordinance (ſaith <hi>Peter.</hi>) Let euery ſoule bee ſubiect to the higher powers (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> in the beginning of this Chapter.) And in the third to <hi>Titus;</hi> Put them in remembrance that they be ſubiect to Principalities and Powers, and that they be obedient to euery good worke. So then, wee muſt bee ſubiect ſimply and without exception; obedient only in thoſe things that are good. Good for our ſelues, good for the Church, or good for the Common-wealth wherein we liue. And we muſt not our ſelues bee Iudges what is good, but ſubmit our owne iudgement to the iudgement of our Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, except we find that the things commanded bee plainly and directly forbidden in the Word, in which caſe wee muſt bee ſubiect ſtill, though not obedient. This was (you ſee) the Doctrine of Chriſt, this was the Doctrine of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> no other Doctrine taught or thought of in the Chriſtian world, for ſixe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7541:6"/>hundred yeares after Chriſt, as may appeare, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Books and Writings of all the Fathers of thoſe ſeuerall ages, but ſpecially by the practice and example of all thoſe noble and renowned Martyrs, which liued in the very heate of the Furnace, in thoſe long and bloudie times, contayning the ſucceſſion of ten ſeuerall Perſecutions, vnder the moſt cruell Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Emperours. Againſt whom they neuer offered to make head, neuer went about to practiſe treaſon, neuer attempted to take vp armes; notwithſtanding that they were (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> witneſſeth) both more in number, and greater in ſtrength, then any other Nation or Kingdome in the whole world, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were otherwiſe inſtructed; where they could not yeeld obedience, they yeelded their ſubic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, neuer drawing any other ſword againſt their enemies, but onely the ſword of the <hi>Spirit;</hi> neuer putting on any other armour for their defence, but onely the armour of <hi>Patience;</hi> neuer thinking of any other ſiege, but onely how they might beſiedge God with their teares and prayers. How hath the pride and tyrannie of that Romiſh <hi>Antichriſt</hi> deſpiſed this Doctrine, and trod it vnder foote? while ſitting in the Temple of God as God; and exalting himſelfe aboue all that is called God; he is not afraid to tell the World that all power is giuen him, both in earth and heauen: and to ſay with <hi>Satan</hi> (in the fourth of <hi>Luke.</hi>) All the Kingdomes of the world are mine, and I giue them to whom I will. In the height of which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, what reuell hath hee kept in the World? What <hi>Tragedies</hi> hath hee brought vpon the Stage? What ſport hath hee made with the Scepters and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7541:7"/>Crownes of Princes? ſetting his feet vpon their necks, roring againſt them in his Bulls, diſcharging their Subiects of their allegeance, expoſing their <hi>Perſons</hi> to all hazards, and proclayming it not onely lawfull but meritorious (when the Trumpet is once blowne and the ſigne giuen out of <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire) for euery pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man to lay violent hands vpon them and to kill them? For ſo <hi>Mariana</hi> the Spaniſh Ieſuite tells vs; that it is a glorious thing to roote out euill Princes from the ſocietie of men, and that it is <hi>ſalutaris cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio,</hi> a wholſome thought, for Princes in a morning, next their hearts, to thinke they liue vpon theſe termes; that if they doe not gouerne as they ought, they may not onely lawfully, but with a great deale of commendation bee killed and murdered. See here what a brawle and what a contrariety is growne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Apoſtles and the Biſhop of Rome, Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors, as they cal themſelues. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doe charge and command the people to bee ſubiect, euen to the moſt wicked Heathen Tyrants that euer liued (and that not onely for feare of wrath, but euen for conſcience ſake:) their ſucceſſors in theſe later times, labour nothing more then to ſteale away the hearts of the people, and to withdraw their obedience and ſubiection from their naturall and true Chriſtian Princes, and to lay them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the ſword of the wicked, if once they refuſe to receiue their marke into their right hands, and to giue their Kingdomes to them. And this they haue not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured without effect. Our owne age hath ſhewed vs tragicall examples in this kind, more then one; and former ſtories tel vs of ſo many, that, had they not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7541:7"/>beene more vnſatiable then the Graue or the Sea, they had ſurely beene glutted long ſince with the bloud of Princes; there being no age ſince this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie began to worke, wherein they haue not made hauocke of one or other. The time will not ſuffer me to purſue theſe miſcreants any longer in their bloudy paths: and therefore I muſt leaue them to the iuſt iudgement of God, which hath begun alreadie with them, and hath made ſuch a breach vpon that Tower of theirs, whoſe ſtrength and height did (but in the former age) ſeeme to terrifie the earth, and threaten heauen; that it begins, you ſee to totter, and is ſo bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered on euery ſide, that wee may eaſily perceiue, it hath but a ſmall time to ſtand.</p>
            <p>But in the meane ſeaſon I am ſorry, that our owne deſects and wants in this very point of obedience, ſhould call mee froth them. Is it poſſible that in a reformed Church; a Church wherein the Romiſh pride and tyranny is ſo iuſtly condemned; a Church wherein the Goſpell is ſo plentifully preached; a Church which hath not locked vp the Word of God: but laid it open, and put it into the hands of all her children; there ſhould be ſo little conſcience made of yeelding obedience to a moſt Chriſtian Magiſtrate, commanding honeſt and lawfull things? To ſpeake nothing of the Ceremonies of our Church, (againſt which there is ſuch an head and oppoſition made by factious ſpirits) which being in their owne nature things indifferent, when once they be agrred vpon by the State, and commanded by authority, doe ceaſe to be indifferent to priuate men, to take or leaue; how are the very Ciuill Lawes of our Land neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7541:8"/>nay, deſpiſed and ſcorned amongſt vs? It was wont to be ſaid of our Lawes (as <hi>Solon</hi> ſaid of his) that they were like vnto Spiders webs; that great flies brake through them at their pleaſure, &amp; little flies were only taken in them. It is not now ſo well. Our Lawes will not hold ſo much as the little flies. The meaneſt that be, will not ſticke to breake them. Let me giue you but one inſtance in this kinde, by which you may iudge of thereſt: And that is the Law that is in force concerning abſtinence from fleſh during the time of Lent. Which abſtinence being enioyned, not out of a ſuperſtitious conceit of holyneſſe or merit, (for as I remember, there is another ſtatute, that layes a penalty vpon all them which ſhall broach any ſuch opinion) muſt needs bee acknowledged to be as honeſt a politique Law, as euer was deuiſed, both for the maintenance of Nauigation, the preſeruation of the young breede of Cattell, &amp; the encreaſe of plenty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs; yet how is this law contemned, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and laught at? It is not now broken (as it was wont: to be) by a few in corners; but it is openly broken, by the poore as well as the rich, in euery mans houſe and ſight, without any ſhame or feare, as if there were no Law at all for it. You will ſay perhaps, that this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes from the negligence of vnder officers, that looke not better to it. Pardon me in that; I know the Officers may be in fault: but this cuill hath a deeper roote. It is want of knowledge, want of inſtruction that hath brought the people to this liberty. They are not plainely taught out of the Word of God; how farre forth they are bound in conſcience to yeeld obedience to humane Lawes. For although it bee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7541:8"/>true, that municipal Lawes doe not bind eternally, nor vniuerſally, nor vnder paine of damnation; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be ſaid to bind the conſcience directly, but by conſequent only: yet I hope it will be granted on all hands, that the fift Commandement bindeth the conſcience, by force whereof wee are bound to yeeld obedience to the Magiſtrate commanding lawfull things, and things profitable for the Commonwealth. And although in the vſe of meates and drinke, and all things elſe that are indifferent, wee bee left vnto our Chriſtian liberty: yet wee muſt not thinke that this liberty is a boundleſſe liberty. For God hath ſet vnto it foure bounds which we cannot paſſe without ſinne: The bound of <hi>Piety;</hi> the bound of <hi>Loyalty;</hi> the bound of <hi>Charity;</hi> the bound of <hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>Sobriety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that although all things bee pure vnto the pure, and all meates lawfull: yet we muſt not eate vnſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, nor vnſanctifiedly, for then, wee breake the bound of <hi>Piety.</hi> Wee muſt not eate to the offence of the Magiſtrate, for then we breake the bound of <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty.</hi> Wee muſt not eate to the offence of the weake, for then we breake the bound of <hi>Charity;</hi> Wee muſt not eate to exceſſe &amp; ſurfetting, for then we breake the bound of <hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>Sobriety.</hi> I could therefore wiſh that thoſe paineful and zealous Preachers, which ſeem? ſo dearely to tender the inſtruction of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, would for a time forbeare theſe May-poles and Morrice-dances, and other ſuch trifles, vpon which they ſpend too much of their ſtrength; and would preſſe this point of Obedience more cloſely to the Conſciences of the people. And I wonder much how it comes to paſſe, that thinking it ſo great a ſinne
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7541:9"/>as they doe, (if any thing that ought to bee knowne be kept backe from the people) that they themſelues, will keepe from them this point of truth, ſo needfull to bee knowne, and ſo profitable for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth to be obſerued. As I muſt needes profeſſe I neuer heard any, nor of any of that humour, that did euer tell his people, that they were bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to obey the Magiſtrate in obſeruing Lent: But contrariwiſe I haue heard of many, that will not ſticke in their owne perſons to giue ill examples, euen vpon Friday nights in Lent and good Friday too. For they haue a conceit, forſooth, that they can neuer be ſufficiently diſtinguiſhed from Papiſts, nor freed from ſuperſtition, except they ſeaſt when the Church appointeth them to faſt; and faſt, when the Church appointeth them to feaſt: which barbarous contempt of Law and order, ioyned with ſuch intollerable pride and wantonneſſe of oppoſition, is not to bee ſuffered in any gouernment. And therefore my hope is, that you which are in place, will looke vnto it. And now, if what I haue ſpoken concerning contempt in this particular, you will vouchſafe to apply to all the reſt, then may this ſuffice, for the firſt duty wee owe vnto the Magiſtrate, which is, Obedience to his Lawes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides obedience to his Lawes, we are bound to ſpeake reuerently &amp; dutifully of him, and not only of him that is ſupreme, but alſo of them that are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate. For they are the Miniſters of God, &amp; therfore we ought to ſpeake wel of them. God hath ſet them in his owne Seate, &amp; therefore who can open his mouth againſt them and bee guiltleſſe? They watch ouer vs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7541:9"/>for our good, and therefore we ought to know them and haue them in ſingular reuerence for their worke ſake. We ſee what paines they take; they are vp early and late, they refuſe no trauaile nor labour to keepe vs in peace and ſafety. All the recompence wee can make them, is only to pray for them and ſpeake well of them. And this is but a verball recompence, and that is the pooreſt recompence that can be, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt needes bee vile and vnthankefull men, that cannot afford them this. But much more vile and wretched they, who (where they are bound by all the Lawes of God and Man to ſpeake all good) delight in nothing more, then to whet and ſet the keeneſt edge vpon their tongues, that ſo they may ſhoote the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned arrowes of their bitter words againſt them. Thoſe two Apoſtles Saint <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; Saint <hi>Iude,</hi> noting a wicked and euill ſort of men, which are like cloudes without water, and like corrupt trees twice dead and pluckt vp by the rootes; among other crimes doe charge them with this as a moſt haynous impiety, that they deſpiſe gouernement, and ſpeake euill of them that be in dignity, contrary to the ſtreight Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God; Thou ſhalt not ſpeake ill of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of thy people: &amp; contrary to the example of his holy Angell, which gaue not railing words when hee contended with <hi>Satan</hi> himſelfe. And if this be ſo hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous an impiety, how much hath this age to anſwere for it, which is, not a little addicted, but in a manner wholly giuen ouer vnto it? wherein we ſee how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a thing it is for children to preſume againſt the ancient; the young againſt the old, the vile againſt the honourable: Wherein the tongue hath ſet on fire
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7541:10"/>the courſe of nature, and mens eares doe itch after no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much, as to heare the reproches of their betters, both in Church and Commonwealth. Two vices there are extreamely oppoſite one vnto another, and both proceede from the tongue: which haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies beene iuſtly accounted the plague and bane of all Commonweales, which are <hi>Flattery</hi> and <hi>Rayling.</hi> Of theſe it is hard to ſay, whether is the worſe. But the latter certainely is more peſtilentiall and infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. For (as <hi>Tacitus</hi> a wiſe Heathen Writer ſaith) <hi>Ambitionem ſcriptoris facile aduerſeris, Obtrectatio &amp; liuor pronis auribus accipiuntur.</hi> Euery mans ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke begins to riſe when he heares a Flatterer: but rayling and obtrectation, thats alwaies willingly and delightfully heard. And whats the reaſon? <hi>Adulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oni foedum crimen ſeruitutis,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>malignitati falſa ſpecies libertatis ineſt.</hi> Flattery doth not only carry with it an odious ſhew of ſlauery, but it is ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh, there is true ſlauery in it indeede. And ſo there is in rayling alſo, for that is a baſe and a ſlauiſh humour too; but yet it carries with it a falſe ſhew of freedome: they that vſe it, are accounted free ſpoken, and free ſpirited men. Therefore you ſee paſquils and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous libels, ſcurrilous inuectiues and bitter ſatyres, are the onely things, that are now eſteemed. Theſe are thought to be ſparkes of truth, caſt into the faces of great Perſonages, by expert and skilfull Markemen: but praiſes and Elogies, though neuer ſo true, neuer ſo deſerued, are harſh, and hatefull in theſe dayes. They are not well endured by ſome humours, no not when they are beſtowed vpon the dead. For this is one of the reaſons giuen vs in print, why there
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7541:10"/>ſhould be no funerall Sermons, becauſe the dead are alwaies praiſed and commended in them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the booke of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> muſt not bee read in Churches, wherein the Author ſaith; Let vs now praiſe famous men and our fathers that begot vs. And <hi>Plinies</hi> long Oration in the praiſe of <hi>Traian</hi> may bee packing out of the world: and ſo may <hi>Pacatus</hi> his too, that he made in the praiſe of <hi>Theodoſius;</hi> and that of <hi>Euſebius</hi> in the praiſe of <hi>Constantine: Panegyricks</hi> are are not for this age. Poore <hi>Roſſe</hi> his <hi>Idea</hi> will not ſell. Such books are in ſmall requeſt; but if a <hi>Iunius Brutus,</hi> or one of <hi>Buchanans</hi> Dialogues, or a <hi>Leicesters</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, or a <hi>Philopatris,</hi> or a <hi>Pruritanus,</hi> or any thing elſe that hath in it any touch or relliſh of the old <hi>Comedy</hi> chance to appear out of darkneſſe; wee ſee what catching and ſnatching there is after ſuch books; ſuch books neuer hang long vpon the Printers hand. As I remember well, when that moſt odious and infamous Libell came firſt our, which masked vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Martin;</hi> a certaine Booke-ſeller (who was knowne to haue diſperſed many of them) being examined vpon oath, (by ſome which were then of greateſt place and authority within this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) how many hee had ſold, made anſwere vpon his oath, that within the ſpace of eight or ten weekes, hee had ſold two thouſand of them: adding further, that hee could haue vttered in the ſame ſpace, two thouſand more, if he had had them, and that there was neuer any booke that pleaſed the people ſo well. Good people you muſt thinke they were the while, the true brood of <hi>Cham,</hi> which could take ſuch plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in a very ſcurrilous and dul booke, a booke where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7541:11"/>in I will not ſay (as one doth) that wounds were ript vp with a laughing countenance: but a booke where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wounds were inflicted vpon the perſons of reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and renowned Prelates, by the pen of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beller, where indeede there were none at all. That people ſhould ſhew themſelues ſo willing to behold the nakedneſſe of their ſpirituall fathers, and that the reproches which were layd vpon them in that Libell (which they ſhould haue lamented and bewailed with many teares, if they had beene true) ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce their hearts, and tickle them with delight and pleaſure, being falſe and faigned; this ſhewes that they were led by the ſame ſpirit, that was in <hi>Cham,</hi> and brought the curſe vpon him. Let vs therefore take heede, how wee vnlooſe our tongues, and ſet them at liberty to ſpeake euill of them that are in authority, or lend our eares to them that doe it: for hee that ſpeaketh, ſometh out his owne ſhame, and hee that loues to heare it, loues to ſee the nakedneſſe of his owne father, and both ſhall be in danger of wrath and iudgement for it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The laſt point of dutie that we owe to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, goes downe into the heart, and there requires a reuerent conceit and eſtimation of him. They that haue ſcanned the nature of thoſe paſſions (that God hath put into the heart of man) obſerue, that reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is a mixt affection, and is compounded of theſe two, <hi>Loue,</hi> and <hi>Feare;</hi> which are the two affections that God requires of vs. The one, as a Father; the other, as a Lord. If I bee your Father, where is my loue? If I be your Lord, where is my feare? So then, we rouerence the Magiſtrate, when wee loue him for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7541:11"/>his goodneſſe; and for his greatneſſe and power doe feare and ſtand in awe of him, being deſirous to keepe our credit and reputation with him, and to be held in his good opinion, and fearing to giue any the leaſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to be brought before him as euill doers. If this affection, this reuerend conceit of the Magiſtrates per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, were (as it ought to bee) truely imprinted in the hearts of men, who ſees not what good it would doe, and what a ſingular holpe and furtherance it would be to all order and gouernement, both in the Church and Common-wealth?) For although it bee true that the feare of God is the true Fountayne of all vertue; yet as Saint <hi>Austen</hi> ſaith of ſlauiſh feare, that it is vnto Charitie, as a needle to the threed, it is many times a meanes to bring in Charitie; ſo we may ſay of the reuerence of man: That though it be not the true Fountayne of vertue, yet it is many times a meanes to bring vs to the true Fountayne. They that ſtand in feare of Men, may eaſily bee led on further to the feare of God. Againe, the feare of Men (though it be not able to breed true godlineſſe:) yet it is a bridle to ſinne: For, <hi>Qui malè agere non verentur, videri ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men verecundantur:</hi> Men that are not afraid to ſinne, are yet afraid and aſhamed, that the world ſhould ſee them ſinne. Now of ſuch there is ſome hope. But when men haue loſt modeſty, which (as <hi>Bernard</hi> truly ſaith) is not only <hi>Gemma in vita &amp; vultu adoleſcentis,</hi> a jewell of great price in the life of a young man: but <hi>Omnium ornatus aetatum;</hi> a beautie to old men, and an ornament to euery age: <hi>Cum non verecundantur;</hi> when they are paſt all ſhame and cannot bluſh; when they haue not only paued their hearts with adamant;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7541:12"/>but alſo couered their faces with braſſe; when they declare their ſinnes, as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and care not to hide them; no, not from the face of the Magiſtrate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: when they haue proceeded ſo farre in ſinne, that not only the feare of God, but alſo the ſhame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of the world, are fled together and departed from them: ſuch men are in a very dangerous eſtate, if not wholly deſperate, there is little hope of ſuch, or none at all. Whereby we may perceiue what a great miſchiefe it is in a Common-wealth, when the faces of thoſe men are made vile, which ſhould be honourable amongſt the people: and when contempt is by Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Raylers caſt vpon them: For when the feare of God and feare of Man, are both taken away; then all the pales, that ſhould keepe men within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of order and obedience, are vtterly broken downe, and a wide gap is laid open to all manner of ſinne and libertie. And therefore they which haue the charge of this Common-wealth, as they loue the beating downe of ſinne, and the growth of vertue, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs; ſo let them endeauour to maintayne to the vtmoſt of all their power, that reuerence which is due to the Princes ſeate: and let them alſo be carefull of their owne credit and reputation. For by that meanes (I am out of doubt) if not the heart of the wicked, yet his colour and his cuſtome will be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what changed; and one of the pales of obedience (at the leaſt) ſhall bee maintayned amongſt vs, and kept ſtanding. And let this ſuffice for the firſt part of my Text, concerning the dignitie and high calling of the Magiſtrate, and our duties that depend vpon it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I am now at length come vnto the ſecond part
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7541:12"/>concerning the dutie of the Magiſtrate, vpon which part you ſhall not need to feare ſo long a diſcourſe, as you had vpon the former. As the time will not beare it, ſo I hope there be not the like need of it. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, you ſee, had need to bee taught their dutie to the Magiſtrates, and therefore I haue ſtood the longer vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that point: but, I hope I may preſume, that the Magiſtrates (to whom I ſpeake) in ſuch abundance of knowledge, wherewith God hath endued them, and after ſo long experience, are not now to learne their dutie. And therefore it may ſuffice to put them in mind of it. It conſiſteth, you ſee, on two parts: whereof,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is the protection of the iuſt and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. For he is the Miniſter of God (ſaith the Apoſtle) for thy good. How for thy good? Not to promote thee to honour; not to giue thee land or liuing, or money out of his purſe (except he will himſelfe.) For in theſe matters of bountie and charitie, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate hath the ſame libertie that other men haue, to open or ſhut his hand, as he ſees cauſe to lead him: But to preſerue thee in thy right, to maintayne thee in thine owne, to defend thee from wrong and iniurie: this is a dutie which the Magiſtrate doth owe vnto thee; a dutie which hee may not denie thee; a dutie vnto which the ſupreme Magiſtrate (at the time of his Coronation) and all that bee vnder him (at the time of their admiſſion vnto their places) bee directly ſworne; a dutie for which God hath ordayned him; a dutie which the nature of his place exacteth of him. And therefore this muſt needs be the good, which the Apoſtle meaneth in this place. Now, though it bee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7541:13"/>true, that the Magiſtrate doth owe this dutie to all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and muſt giue euery man his owne without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons: yet his care ought to bee greateſt for them which are moſt ſubiect to oppreſſion, and by reaſon of their diſabilitie to defend themſelues, lie open to wrong and iniurie. For, as for the great and mightie men here on earth, the Magiſtrate needs not to bee ſo carefull for them: God bleſſe them all, and ſend them his grace to doe right, for they will take no wrong. They are able to bring all the learned coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell to the Barre at an Aſſiſes. They haue Kinred and Alliance in euery corner: they haue witneſſes ready at hand to pleaſure them with an oath: and Iurors at command (ſure Cards:) which (though they know not how to pray for them) know how to faſt for them, if need be. Theſe bee the helps which the great Ones of the world doe fetch out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> (as the Prophet ſpeaks) which makes them altogether careleſſe of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king wrong from their inferiours: and (I would to God) it did not make them as careleſſe of doing wrong vnto them. For ſtill they depopulate, ſtill they racke, ſtill they oppreſſe, and grinde the faces of the poore. Not a Cottage, not a Schoole, not a Colledge, not an Hoſpitall can eſcape their hands. And as for the Church, they make no manner of reckoning what they doe vnto it. All other Robberies are done out of ſight, but Sacriledge is committed at noone-day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, in the ſight and view of the whole world.</p>
            <p>Now the eternall God profeſſeth, that hee hath a controuerſie with theſe <hi>Nimrods</hi> and mightie Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which (like vnto the Oakes of the Forreſt) crie out for more roome, and will ſuffer nothing to grow
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7541:13"/>vp vnder them: which lay the foundation of their houſes in bloud, and build them vp with crueltie, and fill them with the ſpoile of the poore and of the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, making no difference of right, or wrong, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of any thing: I ſay the Lord hath a controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and as it were, a ſuite of law againſt theſe kind of men: and you that be Magiſtrates and men of power and authoritie, are delegates and arbitrators, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitties on Gods part. And therefore as in ſuch caſes, which come before you, wherein the King is made a partie, you are alwayes earneſt and vehement, as you ought to be, in the Kings behalfe, and will not ſuffer any man to pleade or ſpeake againſt him; ſo in theſe cauſes, wherein it pleaſeth God to make himſelfe a partie, if you ſee either the poore Tenant, or the poore Miniſter, or the poore Commoner, or the poore Widow to be oppreſt, if you find their cauſes to bee iuſt and honeſt, you ought not to be lukewarme, but hot and earneſt in them, and to interpoſe your autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie againſt the mightie, and not to ſuffer thoſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Counſailors (that plead before you) to beſtow their eloquence in defence of wrongs. <hi>Non hos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum munus in vſus,</hi> a gift that was neuer beſtowed vpon them to that end: but to put them in mind of that ſpeech of the Apoſtle; <hi>Omnia poſſumus pro ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, contra veritatem nihil poſſumus;</hi> that ſo they may auoid that fearefull Wo, which God (by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi>) hath denounced againſt all them that call euill, good; or good, euill. This if you doe, your reward ſhall bee ſure in the hands of God, and your perſons ſhall bee reuerent and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the ſight of men. For there is nothing in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7541:14"/>world that procures a better opinion, and winnes more honour and loue to the Magiſtrate, then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and protection of the poore. But if you ſhall neglect this dutie (which God forbid:) remember what <hi>Mordecay</hi> ſaid to <hi>Heſter;</hi> If thou hold thy peace, comfort and deliuerance ſhall appeare to the <hi>Iewes</hi> out of another place; but thou and thy houſe ſhall periſh: So, if you (that be Magiſtrates) ſhall hold your peace (when you ſee wrong and oppreſſion) God will ſend comfort and deliuerance from ſome other place, and by ſome other meanes. And ſo wee ſee hee doth. For looke vpon the poore Townſhips that haue beene depopulated. In whoſe hands are they now? I can name you fortie (for a need) within a great deale leſſe then twentie miles of this place, whereof there is not one at this day, that is in the poſſeſſion of him, or any of his name or bloud, that did depopulate it. But as they haue rooted poore men out of their dwellings, ſo God hath rooted them out of theirs. And ſo in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other kind wee ſee a curſe ſtill following goods ill got, and that commonly the third Heire neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyes them. But this is nothing to the Magiſtrate: if he winke at wrong, if the ſeate of iuſtice (that ſhould bee a Sanctuarie to the oppreſſed) doe yeeld no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; if the crie of the poore, and teares of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow be conſtrayned to forſake the earth, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelues before the Throne of God in heauen, when the matter is come to this paſſe, that all men may iuſtly ſay, <hi>Now, O Lord, it is time for thee to lay to thine hand;</hi> when the weake and needy are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to crie, <hi>Helpe Lord! for there is no helpe in man;</hi> when God is enforced to take the cauſe of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7541:14"/>poore into his owne hands, then comfort comes from another place, and then you know what followes in the ſpeech of <hi>Mordecay.</hi> Giue mee leaue therefore to ſhut vp this point with the ſame exhortation (which the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> vſed to the Magiſtrates of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem.) Releeue the oppreſſed, iudge the fatherleſſe, plead for the widow:</hi> that ſo theſe prouerbs, <hi>Might ouercomes Right;</hi> and, <hi>As a man is friended, ſo his cauſe is ended;</hi> and the like, may be vtterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and remembred no more amongſt vs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next point of the Magiſtrates office is to puniſh malefactors, and euill doers. Whereunto you muſt not looke, that wee ſhould exhort them as wee did vnto the former, as earneſtly to execute wrath vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wicked, as to protect the iuſt and innocent. The Biſhops in the primitiue Church had <hi>conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem intercedendi pro reis;</hi> a cuſtome to begge Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and to entreat their pardon of the Magiſtrate; which being called in queſtion, is mightily defended by Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Macedonius:</hi> (I will not take vpon me to iudge, and cenſure that Epiſtle, whether it tend not to too much lenitie and remiſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; yea, or no.) But if the manner of ancient Biſhops was to intreat and begge for pardon; it is not meete for vs to call for vengeance and bloud out of the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. Beſides, I know the old Rule which tells vs; It is better to anſwer God for mercy, then for iuſtice; and ſafer for a Magiſtrate to ſaue the liues of many malefactors, then to caſt away one innocent. For if a malefactor chance to ſcape at one time, the Hand of God is able to reach him at another: but if an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent die, God may receiue him into his mercy, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7541:15"/>will, if he die as a faithfull Chriſtian ought: but it lies not in the power of man to make him ſatisfaction for the wrong. But notwithſtanding all this, they which are in authority had neede to take heede, in what ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they ſhew mercy. For by the example of <hi>Ioſhua</hi> who deſtroyed <hi>Achan</hi> and his houſe, for ſtealing the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> garment contrary to the expreſſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God; by the example of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the men of Iſrael to take vengeance one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and euery man to turne his ſword into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of his owne brother, for their curſed <hi>Idolatry;</hi> by the example of <hi>Phinees</hi> which ſlew the adulterer and adultereſſe both together, and pierced them through with his Iaueline; (in all which places the wrath of God was appeaſed towards the people, ſo ſoone as the execution was done, and not before) I ſay, by theſe and many other examples, that might be produced, it is plaine and euident, that in horrible tranſgreſſions, in haynous and crying ſinnes, there is no way to remoue the wrath of God, and euill from a common State, but by remoouing and taking away the euill and wicked perſons from among the people. Take heede therefore and beware and looke to thy ſelfe, thou that art a tranſgreſſor of the Law. If thou doe euill, feare (ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>) for hee beareth not the ſword in vaine: like the picture of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in a glaſſe-window, or like an Image in a ſtone wall, in whoſe fingers there be no ioynts, and whoſe armes cannot be mooued. For he will draw it forth for the puniſhment of wickedneſſe, and ſinne, and ſmite through the loynes of the vngodly. For as the great <hi>Romane</hi> Oratour could ſay of himſelfe, <hi>Natura me
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7541:15"/>clementem, reſpublica ſeuerum fecit.</hi> So truely I make no queſtion of our Magiſtrates generally through the whole Kingdome, but that they haue hearts of fleſh: that their bowels are full of compaſſion, that nature made them inclineable to mercy and pity.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Molliſsima corda</l>
               <l>Humano generi aare ſe Natura fatetur</l>
               <l>Quae lacrimas dedit.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Wee ſee they giue iudgement vpon Malefactors many times with teares in their eyes: and therefore no doubt their hearts are made of fleſh: but the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of the Common-wealth and the zeale of Gods glory in rooting out ſinne muſt make them ſometimes ſeuere. And ſo wee ſee they are, wee cannot iuſtly charge them that they are any way defectiue in their duty for this point: a great number of malefactors are cut off (at theſe two times of Aſſiſes) within this Kingdome. And a great number, at euery monethly Seſſions in the City of <hi>London.</hi> And yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wee ſee the Goales are no ſooner empty, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently they are filled againe, and the number of male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors is great ſtill; though by no meanes, any way ſo great as it would be, if Iuſtice were wanting. And therefore I could wiſh, if it were poſſible, that there were ſome courſe taken for the better breeding of this kinde of people, that they were not ſuffred to liue in idleneſſe, nor lurke in Ale-houſes (which wee may call as well Peſthouſes:) for in my conſcience they are the very plague and bane of this Kingdome, where all malefactors take their chiefe infection: and that there
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7541:16"/>were ſome courſe alſo taken to compell them to come to Church. To which purpoſe (becauſe I find that ſuch kind of people are ſeldome preſented to the <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall</hi> Courts, and becauſe there is nothing of force ſufficient to keepe people in order, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, if the feare of God be wanting) my deſire and petition is, that the <hi>Statute,</hi> which layes a forfeiture of twelue pence a day, on euery one, that comes not to his Pariſh Church, may bee reuiued and duely execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. A matter giuen in charge (I ſee) and much talked of, but as yet there is nothing done in it. I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it would bee a very great and powerfull meanes to hinder the growth of ſinne, &amp; (as S. <hi>Auſten</hi> ſaith of the Donatiſts, that though they were compelled to come to Church againſt their wils, yet being once there, they were, many of them, taken in the net of Gods Word and made good Chriſtians:) ſo many of theſe idle perſons being compelled to come in, might alſo be taken and made profitable members: which now (for want of breeding and inſtruction) proue nothing elſe but a burden to the earth that beares them, a reproch to their parents, that begat them, and a plague to the Common-wealth, wherein they liue. And with this <hi>Petition</hi> I end.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7541:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
